Finding Aid for Office of Orientation (University of Michigan) records, 1925-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of Orientation (University of Michigan) records
1925-1995
1928-1946
University of Michigan. Office of Orientation.
90191 Bimu D9
University of Michigan office responsible for programs to help students adjust to college life. Records include reports from various university offices and organizations with responsibility for orientation; correspondence and pamphlet material; and printed works directed toward incoming students and their families.
1.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials transferred in two accessions in 1990 by the Office of Orientation (Donor No. 7671/7842 ).
No further accessions are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Office of Orientation has its origin in the Freshman Week created by University of Michigan President C.C. Little in 1927. Little, noting the high attrition rate of Michigan freshmen and acting on the advice of Registrar Shirley Smith, created Freshman Week as an orientation period. Its objectives were to guide incoming students in course selection, to test their intellectual and psychological aptitudes, and to ease the transition from the safety of home to the uncertain life at a large university. The week initially consisted of eight days of activities offered only to freshmen, but this proved too lengthy and too narrow in scope. By 1930 the week was reduced to five days and the scope expanded to include orientation of transfer students. The Office of Orientation served its vital function for the University of Michigan, guiding the first halting steps of initiates to the campus community.
In a 1995 reorganization of student services, the Office of Orientation became part of the newly created Office of New Student Programs.
The Office of Orientation records document, somewhat unevenly, the efforts of the administration of the University of Michigan to ease the transition from high school student to university undergraduate. These records consist of correspondence and published materials sent to incoming students and reports of the various offices involved in orientation. The strength of this record group derives from the face presented by the university in these first documents given to its students. It is illuminating to note what advice the university deems essential for new students, but the tone of presentation is more telling.
The Office of Orientation records span the years 1925-1990, but primarily cover the years 1928-1946. The records came to the library in good order and are organized into three groups: Administration, Orientation Period, and Printed Materials.
Researchers interested in visual images of the orientation process should consult the University of Michigan News and Information Services collection for negatives on freshman week in 1930 and orientation in the 1950s and 1960s.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Students.; College student orientation--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Office of Orientation.
Genre Terms:
College publications.
- Administration, 1934-1945
  The Administration (1934-1945) group consists of four folders of reports from various offices and organizations contributing to orientation.
  - Annual reports (to University Council), 1938-1945 (Box 1)
  - Counselor to new students reports, 1935-1940 (Box 1)
  - Michigan League orientation reports, 1934; 1939 (Box 1)
  - Transfer students reports, 1938-1941 (Box 1)
- Orientation Period, 1925-1972
  The series Orientation Period (1925-1972), consists of six linear inches of correspondence and pamphlets arranged chronologically by year of orientation. These materials are the richest part of the record group, documenting the early efforts of the University and its component elements to advise incoming students. In addition to student orientation materials, there are instructions to faculty advisers.
  - Freshman registration, 1925-1927 (Box 1)
  - Freshman week, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Freshman week, 1928-1929; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Freshman week, 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - 1934-1936 (Box 1)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942 (Box 1)
  - 1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945 (Box 1)
  - 1946 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1972 (Box 1)
- Publications
  The last group, Printed Materials (1967-the present), contains brochures, bulletins such as About Drugs, manuals, and newsletters aimed at incoming students and their parents. These polished publications contain the wealth of information which had been presented in myriad pamphlets in earlier years.
  Other printed materials created by the Office of Orientation include the manuals How Thick Do They Slice the Baloney Around Here: A Students' Guide to the Ins and Outs of U.M. and Rounding Out A2, These handbooks describe the community of Ann Arbor and the University of Michigan, and contain information on community and university services, housing, recreation and entertainment, and university regulations.
  - Unit Publications
    - Bibliographies
      - Read, Read, Read, Bibliography of Suggested Summer Reading for Incoming Freshmen, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Brochures
      - Foreign Student Orientation and Registration, 1969 (Box 2)
      - Freshman Orientations and Registration, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - Freshman Parent Orientation Program, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
      - General, Undated; 1967-1974 (Box 2)
      - Graduate Foreign Language Testing and Orientation Week Information, 1968-1970 (Box 2)
      - Graduate Student Welcome Information, 1994 (Box 2)
      - Parent's Orientation Program, Undated; 1974-1991 (Box 2)
      - Transfer Information and Registration, 1969-1990 (Box 2)
      - Transfer Parent Orientation Program, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Bulletins
      - About Drugs, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - Perspectives, Undated; 1968-1971 (Box 2)
    - Manuals
      - A Guide to the Information Sources at the University of Michigan, 1977 (Box 2)
      - How Thick Do You Slice the Baloney Here?, 1974-1978 (Box 2)
      - An Insider's Guide to U-M, 1987-1995; 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Orientation Activities Supplement, 1967 (Box 2)
      - Parent Handbook, 1986-1995; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Parent Orientation Handbook, 1976-1984 (Box 2)
      - Rounding Out A2, Undated; 1977-1995; 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Maps
      - Campus Maps, Undated (Box 2)
    - Newsletters
      - Michigan Parent, 1988-1994; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Posters, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
    - Programs
      - Welcome to Michigan, 1994 (Box 2)
    - Reports
      - Reach Out, 1993 (Box 2)
      - Final Program Report, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Schedules
      - Freshman Orientation Schedule, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Parent Orientation Program, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Transfer Orientation Schedule, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Sub-Unit Publications
    - Publications Information Center
      - Manuals
        - P.I.C. User's Manual, 1977-1979 (Box 2)